MISSION 48 "IT'S JUST A TYPHOON."
（任务48 台风）
When a person
所谓的“交流障碍症”
has extreme social anxiety,
是指不擅长和人交流的一种症状
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有这种症状的人
Bear in mind…
不过需要注意的是…
POMPH!
（吐气！）
they only struggle to form connections.
这些人只是不擅长社交
-It doesn't mean that they don't want to. -BAM
-但并不表示他们不想和别人有往来 -（砰）
A large typhoon is approaching Honshu Island.
大规模台风正在接近本州
There is a storm warning in effect.
目前也已经发布暴风警报
Shoko, your teacher called.
硝子 老师刚才打来说
There's a storm warning, so you're to wait at home.
因为发布警报了 要你先在家等通知
NO SCHOOL!
（放假了！）
HAPPY BUT CONFLICTED ABOUT THE DAY OFF
（能放假很开心 但都提起干劲要上学 觉得郁闷）
Girls this age are so complicated.
青春期的女孩子心思还真是复杂
KOMI FINDS BAD WEATHER EXCITING.
（天气不好就莫名兴奋的古见同学）
Oh! The power's out.
天啊 停电了
Shoko, are you alright?
硝子 你还好吗？
-FROZEN WITH FEAR -Poor girl. Come here.
-（吓到站不起来） -乖 过来这边
TREMBLE
（发抖）
It was so loud!
雷声很大呢
I'll go look at the breaker with Shosuke.
妈妈和笑介去看看断路器
You wait here.
你等我一下哦
-RING -STARTLE
（铃声 惊吓）
Hello, Komi? Are you at home?
喂？古见同学 你现在在家里吗？
Yes.
对
Oh good. I was worried you'd gone to school.
太好了！我担心你可能去学校了
It looks like your neighborhood is having a power outage.
古见同学家那个地区听说现在停电了
Is everything okay?
状况还好吗？
Um…th-the power's out.
停电是停电了
I-It's fine.
但我没事
Huh? That doesn't sound fine to me.
是吗？听起来好像很不妙
-TODAY'S WEATHER -RUMBLE CRASH
（今日天气 轰隆 碰撞声）
BANG CRASH RUMBLE
（咚咚 砰砰）
Komi, are you alright?
古见同学 你还好吗？
I-I'm okay.
我很好
She doesn't seem okay.
感觉一点也不好
Um.
那个…
Yes?
什么事？
Could we…
我们可以…
talk… a little more?
再多聊一下吗？
Of course.
当然好呀
It has been getting colder outside, hasn't it?
外面差不多变冷了吧？
Yes.
对
Try not to catch a cold, okay?
要小心别感冒
Oh, by the way.
对了
It looks like the storm will be over by afternoon, so we'll probably have school.
据说下午就会解除警报了 下午可能要上学
Yes.
好
Ren Yamai was melancholic.
山井恋正感到忧郁
That day, the typhoon passed and there was school from the afternoon.
那天台风过境后下午恢复上课
But that's not why.
但这并不是原因
She was thinking…
她心里想的是…
Isn't there some way I could see Komi's panties?
有没有什么办法能看到 古见同学的内裤呢？
What is she saying?
这个人在说什么啊？
She couldn't see Komi's panties,
看不到古见同学的内裤
which made her fully melancholic.
令她忧愁不已
Komi…
古见同学…
Wherefore art thou Komi?
为什么你是古见同学呢？
As if to rouse my heart,
你总是扰乱我的内心
she is clad in blue, flaunting tights of inky black.
穿着苍蓝的衣裳与漆黑的裤袜 在我面前晃来晃去
Of course I want to see her panties through her tights!
被裤袜包覆的内裤 我当然想看得不得了！
Must… find a way.
必须想想办法
Find a way to see Komi's panties. Isn't there something…
有没有能看到她内裤的好方法呢？
Oh.
对了
DING!
（灵光一闪）
Eureka!
找到了！
I can tell she's up to no good…
她又在想些有的没的了
-Yeah, and then… -Komi!
-然后啊… -古见同学！
There's a huge puddle in the schoolyard!
操场上有个好大的水坑哦！
Let's go see it!
我们去看看吧！
A puddle?
水坑？
Surely she won't fall for…
她应该不会对这有兴趣…
-NOD -She fell for it!
-（点头） -上钩了！
Woo! Yay!
天啊 好棒！
The stage is set.
准备好了绝佳的舞台
Puddles around the schoolyard.
借由操场上到处都是的水坑
They'll reflect Komi's panties…
映照出古见同学的内裤
It's the perfect strategy!
完美的作战计划！
Oh, Komi.
真棒 古见同学
What sort of panties will you show me?
你会让我看到哪种内裤呢？
Should I stop her?
我该阻止她吗？
Woo! Yay!
好棒 好耶！
Najimi?
驯染
Could you come over here?
可以过来一下吗？
Najimi! Run!
驯染 快逃啊！
Oh, there's wind!
对了 那就靠这阵风吧！
Blow wind blow!
风啊 快吹吧！
Blow to reveal Komi's panties!
为了让我瞄到古见同学的内裤！
Whoa! Oh no!
天啊 不要啊！
Not hers!
不是吹她啦！
I'm left with no other choice!
那就只好执行最后的强硬手段了！
Oops! I fell!
糟糕 不小心跌倒了！
She's blessed! Blessed by god!
备受眷顾！ 古见同学受到神的眷顾啊！
Hey, there's a rainbow!
快看 有彩虹耶！
Who cares about a stupid rainbow!
有没有彩虹根本都无所谓啦！
I just want to see Komi's panties!
我要想办法看到古见同学的内裤…
Who cares about panties!
我不在乎内裤的事了！
Ren Yamai. Purification complete.
山井恋 净化完成
What was that?
刚才那是怎样？
-TWO DAYS LATER -AH, I WANT TO SEE KOMI'S PANTIES
（两天后 我想看古见同学的内裤）
HOW… WITH A STRAIGHT FACE?
（一脸认真想这种事？）
MISSION 49 "IT'S JUST A FANTASY."
（任务49 妄想）
Of all the girls in our class…
假如要跟班上女生交往…
-Who would you date? -SHIGEO CHIARAI
你们会选谁？
-MONO SHINOBINO -TAISEI SONODA
（忍野裳乃 园田大势）
Let's discuss it in detail.
仔细谈谈吧
-What are they up to? -HITOHITO TADANO
这些人在搞什么？
OF ALL THE GIRLS, WHO WOULD YOU DATE? NAJIMI VERSION
（想跟班上哪个女生交往？ 驯染篇）
Something started!
有故事开演了！
That was wild.
吓死我了
We rode so many attractions!
我们玩了好多设施哦！
I'm pretty tired.
我已经累了
Let's take a break.
那休息一下吧
We can get some ice cream.
吃个冰淇淋
Wow, this flavor is great!
天啊 这个口味超好吃
Gotcha!
有破绽！
Don't let your guard down so much!
谁叫你老是破绽百出！
Let's go on that ride next!
“那接着去坐那个吧”
Whoa, you want to keep at it?
“天啊 你还要玩啊？”
It would be fun, like hanging out with a buddy..
这种像朋友间的互动真的不错
Dabbing ice cream on your nose. That's a high score.
鼻子沾到冰淇淋的部分 能得到很多分呢
So that's how they decide!
是用这种方法在决定吗？
-AGARI VERSION -It started again!
-（上理篇） -又开始了！
She's still not here…
她还不来吗？
I-I'm sorry!
抱歉！
I was deciding what to wear, and ran behind schedule.
我在挑要穿哪件衣服 结果就迟到了！
Did you wait long?
你等很久了吗？
No, not long. I just got here.
不会 没等多久 我也刚到
Oh good.
那就好
You're wearing such a bold outfit today.
你今天穿衣风格好像比较大胆呢
Oh! That's, uh…
其实是因为…
If it's you, I thought it'd be okay…
我觉得如果是你的话没关系…
What's okay?! Okay to do what?
“没关系”是什么意思？ 是指做什么没关系？
You mean her boobs?
果然是好在胸部吗？
They're the worst.
好差劲
OF ALL THE GIRLS, WHO WOULD YOU DATE? YAMAI VERSION
（想跟班上哪个女生交往？ 山井同学篇）
Hey, cheer up already, alright?
你就不要生气了 好吗？
Maybe the food wasn't great, but still.
就只是餐点有点不好吃而已嘛
Close your mouth.
少啰嗦
You've got poor taste. That's why this happened.
都是因为你的品味太差 才会变成这样
I said I was sorry.
抱歉啦
Oh yeah. Here.
对了 这给你
It's been a month, right?
我们交往一个月了吧？
For our anniversary.
想当作纪念送你
What is this? They're awful!
这是什么啊？好土哦！
You really have no taste.
你的眼光真的糟透了
Let's go already! Ugh.
差不多该走了啦！
As she says it, the new earrings glitter on her ears.
山井嘴上虽这么说 但耳朵上的新耳环闪闪发光
Thank you so much!
谢谢招待！
These guys.
这些人
They don't know Yamai's true self!
根本不懂山井同学的本性！
OF ALL THE GIRLS, WHO WOULD YOU DATE? NAKANAKA VERSION
（想跟班上哪个女生交往？ 中中篇）
Oh, not there. There's a chest up to the right.
不是那边 有个宝箱 所以要走右上方
To the right?
右边？
I told you, not there. Give me that. I'll get it.
都说不是那里了 给我 我帮你拿
Wow! You got it!
好厉害 拿到了！
Don't you know it!
我说得没错吧？
And then we'd play the game together.
之后两个人继续融洽地玩游戏
Wow. So cute.
天啊 好可爱
What is this feeling?
这是什么感觉？
That chill vibe. It's exquisite.
两个人一起在家里 懒洋洋度过的气氛真棒
That would be pretty nice.
这场景的确不错耶
OF ALL THE GIRLS, WHO WOULD YOU DATE? INAKA VERSION
（想跟班上哪个女生交往？ 井中篇）
My name is Shinobino.
我叫忍野
I'm a houseboy for a great teacher in the countryside.
在这偏僻的乡下 担任一位老师的书生
-A monologue? -Hey!
-还有独白？ -喂！
I've harvested lots of vegetables again this year!
今年也采收了很多好吃的蔬菜唷！
This is Inaka.
她是井中小姐
She's the daughter of the family next door.
是老师隔壁人家的女儿
Shinobino. Go on, try one!
忍野先生 你拿一根尝尝看呗
Alright. Just one.
好 那我就吃一根
You like it?
好吃呗？
I love to watch her from afar.
我喜欢在远处望着她
That's why I take the long way home.
所以回家都故意绕远路看她
How sophisticated!
好老成啊！
The way Inaka is from the country but thinks she's hiding it.
她自认为有瞒住自己是乡下人的事
It's so cute.
这点很可爱
Oh, they noticed.
是喔 原来被发现了？
OF ALL THE GIRLS, WHO WOULD YOU DATE? MAKERU VERSION
（想跟谁交往？ 真华留篇）
Thank you.
谢谢惠顾
Ooh. It's cold.
天啊 好冷哦
Let's hurry home and eat something warm.
快点回家吃点热的吧
Oh. Yes.
好 就这么办
I'll race you home!
那就跑回家吧 看谁比较快！
No fair!
不公平！
Yay! I won!
好耶 是我赢了！
Huh? Wow, that's awesome.
什么？这情境简直太棒了！
Chiarai, you like Makeru don't you!
地洗井很喜欢真华留呢
Yadano's really cute?!
矢田野同学真的很可爱？
And now for the pièce de résistance. Komi.
最后就是众所期待的古见同学
You wanna do it?
要开始了吗？
I'll make a perfect episode.
绝对要想出很棒的妄想故事
Their game has changed?
是不是偏离主要目的了？
5 MINUTES LATER
（五分钟后）
This is tough.
真伤脑筋
I can't imagine it.
完全想象不出来
10 MINUTES LATER
（十分钟后）
Being alone with Komi?
跟古见同学独处
It's just not possible!
根本是不可能的任务！
I'm woefully unworthy!
能力压倒性不足啊！
OF ALL THE GIRLS, WHO WOULD YOU DATE? KOMI VERSION
（想跟班上哪个女生交往？ 古见同学篇）
That was delicious!
我吃饱了
I'll do the dishes.
那我来洗碗吧
We can decide using rock, paper, scissors then.
不然猜拳决定好了
Rock, paper…
剪刀、石头…
Oh, Komi. You can rest.
没关系啦 古见同学去休息…
Uh… Thank you.
好吧 谢谢你
-Whoa! -HOW CAN I IMAGINE THAT!
-天啊！ -（我在乱想什么啊？）
That scared me!
吓我一跳！
Why's he screaming?
他在乱叫什么？
Is he alright?
没事吧？
MISSION 50 "IT'S JUST A CAT CAFE."
（任务50 猫咪咖啡厅）
All the cute kitties are here!
可爱的猫咪集结了
We're featuring cat cafes!
猫咪咖啡厅特辑！
Today we look at some trendy cat cafes!
今天要详细采访 时下最受欢迎的猫咪咖啡厅！
I SAW IT ON A NEWS PROGRAM
（看到了这个新闻节目）
Wow, a cat cafe?
这样啊 猫咪咖啡厅吗？
Hm.
是喔
-COME WITH ME? -Sorry I can't.
-（一起去吧） -抱歉 不行
Quick response!
立刻拒绝！
Oh, yeah. You have a cat allergy.
对了 你对猫咪过敏吧
Yeah, I do.
就是说啊
I wish I could kiss those cute kitties though.
我是多么想亲可爱的猫咪呀
Ew.
好恶心
-See ya! -WHAT ABOUT YOU?
-辛苦了！ -（那只野同学呢？）
Huh? Me?
什么？你问我吗？
Yea…
好…
Ah.
这个嘛
Oh, sorry. I already have plans.
抱歉 我今天也有事要做
Why don't you invite someone else?
你去约其他人怎么样？
How about Onemine?
比方说尾根峰同学
-You called? -She came!
-你叫我吗？ -来了！
Try inviting her!
约约看吧！
CAT CA…
（猫…）
Sure!
好呀
Dependable Onemine!
不愧是尾根峰同学！
Welcome!
欢迎光临！
Ta-da! I came too!
惊喜！我也跟来了！
We did come together, so I knew that.
我知道 我们是一起来的
Good kitty.
好乖喔
Hm? Who's this?
什么？怎么啦？
KOMI GOES INTO SHOCK FROM CUTENESS OVERLOAD
（因猫咪太过可爱 而受冲击的古见同学）
STARTLE
（惊吓）
Wow, it's my first time here.
原来是这种感觉 我是第一次来
They really let the cats roam free.
猫咪在这里都这么自由啊
That one's sleeping.
也有在睡觉的
Wow, they're all so tame.
天啊 每只猫果然都很亲人
So friendly!
和蔼可亲！
-NONE OF THE CATS APPROACH KOMI -SILENCE
（没有猫咪接近古见同学 安静）
Kaede, did the cats come to you?
有猫咪过去小枫那边吗？
-So many! -There, there. You're such good kitties!
-超多的！ -好乖哦 大家都是好孩子
K-Kaede? Kaede!
小枫？小枫同学！
-VERY JEALOUS -EXHALE
（非常羡慕 呼气）
I've never seen that face before.
第一次看到她这种表情
Komi, look! That cat is sleeping.
古见同学 你看 那边有猫咪在睡觉
Try petting it!
你去摸摸它吧！
If it's asleep, it won't run away.
既然在睡觉 应该不会逃掉
LOITER
（观望）
-Socially awkward with cats too! -IT'S SLEEPING. I MIGHT BOTHER IT.
-面对猫咪会有交流障碍症 -（它在睡觉 可能会造成困扰）
CHOCOLAT (FEMALE)
（巧克力 雌）
My name is Chocolat.
我的名字叫巧克力
I'm the boss of this cat cafe.
是这间猫咪咖啡厅的老大
Once again today, the cafe is full of idiotic people.
今天也一如往常 店里来了一大群愚蠢的人类
First, let me say this.
我丑话说在前头
I hate being touched by people.
我讨厌人类摸我
Humans don't think about cats' feelings and just force themselves on us.
人类完全不考虑猫的心情 只会乱摸一通
-My freshly groomed coat gets ru-- -Boss!
-好不容易整理好的毛都… -老大！
There's a scary human--
今天来了个可怕的人…
Don't interrupt when I'm talking!
我在说话 不准插嘴！
SILVER VINE
（木天蓼）
So what is it?
所以怎么了？
There's a scary human here.
今天有个可怕的人类
I don't know what she's thinking.
不知道她在想什么
Her aura is scary!
气场很吓人！
What do you mean, aura?
还扯到气场是怎样？
Which one is it?
是哪一个？
Uh…
我看看…
That's her! With long, black hair.
就是她 那个黑色长发的人类
She's just a regular human.
不就只是个普通的人类嘛…
BLACK CAT!
（黑猫！）
LOVES BLACK CATS
（我爱黑猫）
There's certainly something unknowable about her.
的确有种摸不透的感觉
Let's keep an eye on her for now.
再稍微观察一下吧
Look at that. She can't touch us at all.
那个人类是怎样？ 完全摸不到我们嘛
Did you want a companion that badly? Pitiful human.
你就这么希望猫咪理你吗？臭人类
Humans are such a pain.
真是麻烦的人类
Huh? Boss? Where are you going?
奇怪 老大 你要去哪里？
Boss! Boss!
老大！是老大耶！
Boss. Are you serious?
老大 你是认真的吗？
Are you going to her? To that female…
老大要去那个女人身边吗？
Wow.
真厉害
Oh, wow!
天啊 真少见！
Chocolat never approaches people.
巧克力平常不太会亲近人
Meow.
喵
AWW
（心动）
What an adorable black cat!
好可爱的黑猫哦
Yeah!
对啊
FROM ONEMINE
（寄件人 尾根峰）
I should have gone.
早知道就去了
He wanted Komi to practice inviting other people.
为了让古见同学练习邀约别人
So Tadano stayed home even though he didn't have plans.
明明没事做却婉拒邀请的只野同学
Total letdown.
意志消沉
HE SPENT THREE DAYS THINKING ABOUT MAKING IT HIS LOCKSCREEN
（烦恼要不要设成 待机画面长达三天）
MISSION 51 "IT'S JUST THE 'I LOVE YOU GAME'."
（任务51 是“我爱你”游戏）
Komi, um.
古见同学 我…
It's, uh.
那个…
Hey.
我…
I love you.
我爱你
What is the "I Love You Game"?
所谓的“我爱你游戏”
Say "I love you."
是指说出“我爱你”后
If the other person reacts by smiling or blushing, you win.
对方若是忍不住微笑或害羞就赢了
You can phrase it how you like.
也可以在说法上下功夫
-And create a specific situation. -I love you.
-或是特地制造情境 -我爱你
Anyhow, if you blush you lose.
总之听到“我爱你”后害羞就算输了
LOSE
（输了）
Komi was lured into this game by Yamai.
山井同学对古见同学 玩起了这个游戏
Oh Komi, you're so tough!
天啊 古见同学好强哦！
Yeah but I just wanted to tell Komi I love her.
其实我只是想对 古见同学说“我爱你”
I don't care if I win or lose.
输赢根本无所谓
As long as I can tell Komi I love her.
只要能对她说“我爱你”就行
Alright, it's your turn. Now say it to me.
那这次换古见同学说了 换你对我说说看
Here it comes! I've been waiting for this!
来了 我就是在等这个！
I can legally hear Komi say she loves me.
能让古见同学
I've been waiting!
合法说爱我的场面！
Alright, what are you going to say to me, Komi?
来吧 你打算怎么对我说？古见同学
What? "I?"
要说什么啊？“我”？
Hey, c'mon. Try saying it, Komi.
快说说看嘛 古见同学
"I?" "I love?"
“我”？“爱”？
"I love y…"
“我爱你…”
She started grinning before Komi began, so she lost.
还没开始就忍不住笑出来 所以输了
Let's go again!
再来一次！
What? What are you doing?
什么？在做什么呀？
Just when it was getting good!
竟敢在绝佳时机来破坏我的好事！
Hm? We're not doing anything.
什么？没有啦 我们也没在干吗啊
Right, Komi?
对吧？古见同学
Really?
真的吗？
Yes, really!
真的啦！
Playing hide and seek by yourself would be way more fun.
一个人玩捉迷藏 会比这话题有趣一百倍呢
Go try it!
你去旁边玩吧！
Oh, by the way, Komi.
对了 古见同学
I love you.
我爱你哦
Trickster!
这家伙！
You did a spit-take didn't you?
你刚才笑出来了吧？
I win!
我赢了！
DENIES
（摇头否认）
Alright, Tadano, you judge!
好吧 那只野同学来判定
Me?
我？
IT WAS SO SUDDEN SHE DID A SPIT-TAKE
（只是因为太突然 吓到才笑出来）
No blush so she's safe.
她没害羞 所以不算输
-Playing favorites! -KOMI HAS BEGUN TO ENJOY THIS GAME
-你偏袒她！ -（越来越有趣了）
I love you!
我爱你！
I love you.
我爱你
Komi's so tough!
古见同学好强！
It has come to this. Time for the big guns.
事已至此 只能拿出最终兵器了
Tadano, come on!
只野同学 上吧！
Me?
我吗？
No no no! That would be… you know!
不行啦 这怎么行啊？对吧？
-What's with the pause? -NOD
-刚才那阵停顿是怎样？ -（点头）
There's nothing to be embarrassed about! It's just a game!
害羞什么？只是玩个游戏而已！
If you protest, you look suspicious!
抗拒成这样 看起来反而像真的有意思
-There's no escape! -TADANO, YOU GET IT DON'T YOU?
-这下逃不掉了！ -（只野同学 知道该怎么做吧？）
Outsmarted again by their cunning tactics!
可恶 偏偏在这时这么能言善道！
-Antenna-looking onion-head! -ANTENNA-LOOKING ONION-HEAD
-你这个呆毛洋葱头！ -（呆毛洋葱头）
Hurry, hurry!
快点！
It's a game. Just a game!
这是游戏 这只不过是个游戏！
I don't have to be shy. Just pretend it's a joke.
不要害羞就能当成玩笑带过了
Alright!
好！
-I… -You lose!
-我爱… -你输了！
Hang on. The person speaking can't smile?
等等 说的人也不能笑吗？
Of course not! It's embarrassing to say it after all.
那当然啊 说的人也会害羞
Oh, right. I guess so.
不过也是啦
-I LOVE YOU GAME OVER -Here's some trivia you can use!
-（我爱你游戏结束） -明天也能用上的小知识！
-Komi reacted less than I thought. -Wombats poop cubes.
-古见同学的反应意外地平淡 -袋熊的大便是四角形的
I guess it wouldn't mean anything to her if I said it.
也对啦 我对她说这种话 她才不会在意呢！
-Can't use that! -Can too!
-用不上！ -用得上！
I guess I worried for nothing.
我在意过头了！
-Can't use it. -Sure you can!
-用不上 -用得上！
-Don't fall in! -Oh, me too!
-去方便一下吧！ -我也要去！
Let me go!
放开我啦！
Let me go! Let me go!
放开我 给我放手！
"I'm glad they stopped him."
“幸好有人阻止他说”
and,
以及…
"I wish he had said it." were the two feelings in Komi's heart.
“但也有点想听他说” 两种心情交织的古见同学
BONUS SCENE
（片尾彩蛋）
Welcome!
欢迎光临
Chocolat also stamped her paw in Komi's Book of Friends.
也请巧克力在《古见友人账》 盖下肉球印章的古见同学
85 left to go meow.
离目标还有85人喵
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：吴敬美